Can I say how delighted I am to be away
هل أستطيع القول كم أنا مسرور بالبعد
from the calm of Westminster and Whitehall? (Laughter)
عن الهدوء في وستمنستر و وايت هول؟
This is Kim, a nine-year-old Vietnam girl,
هذه كيم، فتاة فيتنامية عمرها تسعة سنوات،
her back ruined by napalm,
تلف ظهرها بالنابلم،
and she awakened the conscience of the nation of America
وقد أيقظت ضمير الأمة الأمريكية
to begin to end the Vietnam War.
لبداية نهاية حرب فيتنام.
This is Birhan, who was the Ethiopian girl
هذه بيرهان، التي كانت الفتاة الاثيوبية
who launched Live Aid in the 1980s,
التي بدأت الإعانات المباشرة في الثمانينات،
15 minutes away from death when she was rescued,
عندما تم إنقاذها قبل 15 دقيقة من الموت،
and that picture of her being rescued is one that went round the world.
وتلك الصورة لها عند إنقاذها تم تداولها عبر العالم.
This is Tiananmen Square.
هذا هو ميدان تيانانمين.
A man before a tank became a picture
صورة لرجل يقف في مواجهة دبابة
that became a symbol for the whole world of resistance.
أصبحت رمز، لكل العالم، للمقاومة.
This next is the Sudanese girl,
التالي هو الطفلة السودانية،
a few moments from death,
قبل لحظات من الموت،
a vulture hovering in the background,
نسر يحوم في الخلفية،
a picture that went round the world
صورة تنقلت حول العالم
and shocked people into action on poverty.
وصدمت الناس للعمل على معالجة الفقر.
This is Neda, the Iranian girl
هذه ندى، الشابة الإيرانية
who was shot while at a demonstration with her father in Iran
التي قتلت أثناء المظاهرت مع والدها في إيران
only a few weeks ago, and she is now the focus, rightly so,
قبل أسابيع قليلة فقط، وهي الآن تحت الضوء، وهي على حق،
of the YouTube generation.
لجيل اليوتيوب.
And what do all these pictures and events have in common?
وما هو الرابط المشترك لكل هذه الصور والأحداث؟
What they have in common is what we see unlocks
المشترك بينهم هو ما نراه حبيساً
what we cannot see.
وما لا نستطيع رؤيته.
What we see unlocks the invisible ties
ما نراه حبيساً: الروابط الخفية
and bonds of sympathy that bring us together
وأواصر التعاطف التي تجمعنا
to become a human community.
لنصبح المجتمع الإنساني.
What these pictures demonstrate is that
ما تثبته هذه الصور هو
we do feel the pain of others,
نحن نحس بآلالام الآخرين،
however distantly.
ولكن بفارق كبير.
What I think these pictures demonstrate
ما أعتقد أن هذه الصور تثبته
is that we do believe in something bigger than ourselves.
أننا نعتقد في شئ أكبر من أنفسنا.
What these pictures demonstrate is
ما تثبته هذه الصور هو
that there is a moral sense across all religions, across all faiths,
أن هناك إحساس أخلاقي بين كل الديانات، بين كل العقائد،
across all continents -- a moral sense that
بين كل القارات -- إحساس أخلاقي
not only do we share the pain of others,
بأننا لا نتشارك آلالام الآخرين فقط،
and believe in something bigger than ourselves
ونعتقد في شيئ أكبر من أنفسنا
but we have a duty to act when we see things
لكن لدينا واجب التحرك عندما نرى الأشياء
that are wrong that need righted,
الخطأ وتحتاج الى تصحيح،
see injuries that need to be corrected,
نرى الجروح التى تحتاج لعناية،
see problems that need to be rectified.
نرى المشاكل التي تحتاج الى حلول.
There is a story about Olof Palme, the Swedish Prime Minister,
هناك حكاية عن أولوف بالمي، رئيس الوزراء السويدي،
going to see Ronald Reagan in America in the 1980s.
ذاهباً لرؤية رونالد ريغان في أمريكا في الثمانينات.
Before he arrived Ronald Reagan said --
قبل أن يصل قال رونالد ريغان --
and he was the Swedish Social Democratic Prime Minister --
وقد كان رئيس الوزراء السويدي ديموقراطي إشتراكي--
"Isn’t this man a communist?"
"أليس هذا الرجل شيوعي؟"
The reply was, "No, Mr President, he’s an anti-communist."
الإجابة كانت، "لا، سيدي الرئيس، أنه معادي للشيوعية."
And Ronald Reagan said, "I don’t care what kind of communist he is!"
وقال رونالد ريغان، " لا أهتم أي نوع من الشيوعيين هو!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Ronald Reagan asked Olof Palme,
سأل رونالد ريغان أولوف بالمي،
the Social Democratic Prime Minister of Sweden,
رئيس الوزراء الإشتراكي الديموقراطي،
"Well, what do you believe in? Do you want to abolish the rich?"
"حسناً، ما الذي تراه ؟ هل تريد إلغاء الدول الغنية؟"
He said, "No, I want to abolish the poor."
فكان رده، "لا أنا أريد إلغاء الدول الفقيرة."
Our responsibility is to let everyone have the chance
مسئوليتنا هي توفير الفرصة للجميع
to realize their potential to the full.
لتحقيق قابليتهم الى أقصاها.
I believe there is a moral sense and a global ethic
أعتقد أن هناك حس أخلاقي وأخلاق عالمية
that commands attention from people of every religion
الذي يجذب إنتباه الناس من كل المناطق
and every faith, and people of no faith.
وكل المعتقدات، والناس الذين لا يؤمنون.
But I think what's new is that we now have the capacity
لكن أعتقد أن الجديد هو أن لدينا الآن الإمكانية
to communicate instantaneously across frontiers
للتواصل على الفور عبر الحدود
right across the world.
تماماً في كل أنحاء العالم.
We now have the capacity to find common ground
نحن الآن لدينا الإمكانية لإيجاد أرضية مشتركة
with people who we will never meet,
مع الناس الذين لم نلتقيهم أبداً
but who we will meet through the Internet and through
لكن الذين سنلتقيهم عبر الإنترنت وعبر
all the modern means of communication;
كل وسائل الإتصالات العصرية،
that we now have the capacity to organize
أننا الآن لدينا الإمكانية لتنظيم
and take collective action together
وأخذ تحركات إنتقائية معاً
to deal with the problem or an injustice
للتعامل مع المشكلة أو الظلم
that we want to deal with;
الذي نريد التعامل معه،
and I believe that this makes this a unique age in human history,
وأعتقد أن ذلك يجعل هذا وقتاً فريداً في تاريخ الإنسانية،
and it is the start of what I would call
وهي بداية ما أسميه
the creation of a truly global society.
خلق المجتمع العالمي الصحيح.
Go back 200 years when the slave trade was
لنذهب الى الوراء 200 عاماً عندما كانت تجارة الرقيق
under pressure from William Wilberforce and all the protesters.
تحت الضغط من وليم ويلبرفورس وكل المحتجين.
They protested across Britain.
لقد تظاهروا عبر بريطانيا.
They won public opinion over a long period of time.
وكسبوا الرأي العام على مدى فترة طويلة من الزمن
But it took 24 years for the campaign to be successful.
لكن إستغرق الأمر 24 عاماً للحملة لتصبح ناجحة.
What could they have done with the pictures that they could have shown
ما قاموا به مع الصور التي قد تظهر
if they were able to use the modern means of communication
لو كان بمقدورهم إستخدام وسائل الإتصالات
to win people’s hearts and minds?
لكسب قلوب الناس وعقولهم؟
Or if you take Eglantyne Jebb,
أو اذا أخذتم إقلانتاين جيب،
the woman who created Save the Children 90 years ago.
المرأة التي أسست "انقذوا الأطفال" قبل 90 سنة مضت.
She was so appalled by what was happening in Austria
كانت مفزوعة جداً بما يحدث في النمسا
as a result of the First World War and what was happening to children
كنتيجة للحرب العالمية الأولى وما يحدث للأطفال
who were part of the defeated families of Austria,
الذين كانوا جزء من الأسر المهزومة في النمسا،
that in Britain she wanted to take action,
وأنها في بريطانيا أرادت عمل شئ،
but she had to go house to house,
لكن كان عليها الذهاب من منزل الى منزل
leaflet to leaflet, to get people to attend a rally
منشور الى منشور، لحث الناس على حضور الحشد
in the Royal Albert Hall
في قاعة ألبرت الملكية
that eventually gave birth to Save the Children,
التي أوجدت في نهاية المطاف "أنقذوا الأطفال"،
an international organization that is now fully recognized
المنظمة الدولية المعروفة كلياً الآن
as one of the great institutions in our land and in the world.
كأحد المؤسسات العظيمة في بلدنا وفي العالم.
But what more could she have done
لكن ماذا أكثر كان بإمكانها فعله
if she’d had the modern means of communications available to her
اذا كان لديها وسائل الإتصالات متوفرة لها
to create a sense that the injustice that people saw
لخلق إحساس الظلم الذي رأه الناس
had to be acted upon immediately?
كان لزاماً العمل عليه في الحال؟
Now look at what’s happened in the last 10 years.
الآن أنظر لما حدث في ال 10 سنوات الماضية.
In Philippines in 2001, President Estrada --
في الفلبين في 2001، الرئيس إسترادا--
a million people texted each other about the corruption of that regime,
مليون شخص تراسلوا نصياً حول الفساد في تلك الحكومة،
eventually brought it down and it was, of course, called the "coup de text." (Laughter)
أدت في نهاية المطاف لإسقاط الحكومة، وكانت بالطبع، اطلق عليه " إنقلاب النص."
Then you have in Zimbabwe the first election under Robert Mugabe a year ago.
بعدها في زيمبابوي الإنتخابات الأولى في سنوات حكم موغابي قبل عام.
Because people were able to take mobile phone photographs
لأنه كان بمقدور الناس أخذ صور بالهواتف النقالة
of what was happening at the polling stations, it was impossible
لما يجري في مراكز الإقتراع، كان مستحيلاً
for that Premier to fix that election in the way that he wanted to do.
لذلك الرئيس أن يجري الإنتخابات بالطريقة التي يريد.
Or take Burma and the monks that were blogging out,
أو خذ بورما و الرهبان الذين يدونون،
a country that nobody knew anything about that was happening, until these blogs
الدولة التي لم يعرف أي شخص عنها حتى تلك المدونات
told the world that there was a repression,
أخبرت العالم أن هناك قمع،
meaning that lives were being lost
ما يعني أن هناك أرواح تُزهق
and people were being persecuted and Aung San Suu Kyi,
والناس يُعدموا وآنغ سان سوو كيو،
who is one of the great prisoners of conscience of the world,
الذي هو أحد أعظم سجناء الرأي العام في العالم،
had to be listened to.
يجب الإستماع إليه.
Then take Iran itself, and what people are doing today:
بعدها خذ إيران نفسها، وما يفعله الناس اليوم،
following what happened to Neda,
عقب ما حدث لندى،
people who are preventing the security services of Iran finding those people
الناس الذين يعملون في الخدمات الأمنية في إيران يتعقبون أولئك الناس
who are blogging out of Iran, any by everybody who is blogging,
الذين يدوّنون الى خارج إيران،
changing their address to Tehran, Iran,
يغيّرون عناوينهم الى طهران، إيران،
and making it difficult for the security services.
ويجعلون الأمر صعباً للجهات الأمنية.
Take, therefore, what modern technology is capable of:
خذ، بالتالي، ما هي إمكانية التكنلوجيا الحديثة:
the power of our moral sense allied to the power of communications
قوة إحساسنا الأخلاقي تحالف مع قوة الإتصالات
and our ability to organize internationally.
ومقدرتنا على التنظيم عالمياً؟
That, in my view, gives us the first opportunity as a community
ذلك، في نظري، يعطينا أول فرصة كمجتمع
to fundamentally change the world.
لتغيير العالم جذرياً.
Foreign policy can never be the same again. It cannot be run by elites;
السياسة الخارجية لن تكون كما كانت بعد الآن. لا يمكن تسييرها بواسطة النُخب.
it’s got to be run by listening to the public opinions of peoples who are blogging,
يتوجب تسييرها بالإستماع الى الرأي العام للمدونين،
who are communicating with each other around the world.
الذين يتواصلون مع بعضهم حول العالم.
200 years ago the problem we had to solve was slavery.
قبل 200 سنة مضت كانت المشكلة التي علينا حلها هي العبودية.
150 years ago I suppose the main problem in a country like ours
150 سنة مضت أفترض أن المشكلة الرئيسية في بلد مثل بلدنا
was how young people, children, had the right to education.
كانت كيف أن الشباب، الأطفال، لديهم الحق في التعليم.
100 years ago in most countries in Europe, the pressure was for the right to vote.
قبل 100 سنة مضت في معظم الدول الأوروبية، كان الضغط لحقوق التصويت.
50 years ago the pressure was for the right to social security and welfare.
قبل 50 سنة مضت كان الضغط لحقوق الضمان الإجتماعي والرفاهية.
In the last 50-60 years we have seen fascism, anti-Semitism, racism, apartheid,
وفي ال 50 الى 60 سنة شهدنا الفاشية، معاداة السامية، العنصرية، الفصل العنصري،
discrimination on the basis of sex and gender and sexuality;
التمييز على أساس الجنس والنوع والنشاط الجنسي.
all these have come under pressure
كل هذا جاء تحت الضغط
because of the campaigns that have been run by people to change the world.
لأن الإحتجاجات من الناس لتغيير العالم.
I was with Nelson Mandela a year ago, when he was in London.
كنت مع نيلسون مانديلا قبل عام عندما كان في لندن.
I was at a concert that he was attending to mark his birthday
كنت في الحفل الذي حضره إحتفاء بذكرى ميلاده
and for the creation of new resources for his foundation.
ومن أجل خلق موارد جديدة لمؤسسته.
I was sitting next to Nelson Mandela -- I was very privileged to do so --
كنت أجلس بجانب نلسون مانديلا-- كنت صاحب إمتياز للجلوس بجانبه--
when Amy Winehouse came onto the stage. (Laughter)
وعندما جاءت آمي واينهاوس الى المسرح
And Nelson Mandela was quite surprised at the appearance of the singer
وكان نلسون مانديلا مستغرباً جداً لظهور المغني
and I was explaining to him at the time who she was.
كنت أشرح له في ذلك الوقت من تكون هي.
Amy Winehouse said, "Nelson Mandela and I have a lot in common.
قالت آمي واينهاوس، " نلسون مانديلا وأنا لدينا الكثير من الأشياء المشتركة.
My husband too has spent a long time in prison."
زوجي أيضاً قضى وقت طويل في السجن."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Nelson Mandela then went down to the stage
نلسون مانديلا بعدها ذهب الى المسرح
and he summarized the challenge for us all.
ولخّص التحديات لنا جميعاً.
He said in his lifetime he had climbed a great mountain, the mountain
قال أنه خلال حياته تسلّق جبلاً عظيماً، جبل
of challenging and then defeating racial oppression and defeating apartheid.
التحديات وبعدها هزم القهر العنصري وهزم الفصل العنصري.
He said that there was a greater challenge ahead,
قال أن هناك تحديات أكبر في المستقبل،
the challenge of poverty, of climate change -- global challenges
تحدي الفقر، تغير المناخ، تحديات عالمية
that needed global solutions
التي تحتاج الى حلول عالمية
and needed the creation of a truly global society.
وتحتاج لخلق مجتمع عالمي حقيقي.
We are the first generation which is in a position to do this.
نحن أول الأجيال التي هي في وضع القيام بهذا.
Combine the power of a global ethic
تجميع قوة الأخلاق العالمية
with the power of our ability to communicate
مع قوى قدرتنا على الإتصال
and organize globally, with the challenges that we now face,
والتنظيم عالمياً على التحديات التي نواجهها الآن،
most of which are global in their nature.
معظمها عالمية بطبيعتها.
Climate change cannot be solved in one country,
تغير المناخ لا يمكن حله بواسطة دولة واحدة
but has got to be solved by the world working together.
لكن يجب حلها بعمل كل العالم سوياً.
A financial crisis, just as we have seen, could not be solved
والأزمة المالية، التي شهدناها للتو، لا يمكن حلها
by America alone or Europe alone;
بواسطة أمريكا واحدها أو أوروبا وحدها.
it needed the world to work together.
تحتاج كل العالم ليعمل عليها معاً.
Take the problems of security and terrorism and, equally,
خذ مشاكل الأمن والإرهاب و، على السواء،
the problem of human rights and development:
مشكلة حقوق الإنسان والتنمية:
they cannot be solved by Africa alone;
لا يمكن حلهما بواسطة أفريقيا لوحدها.
they cannot be solved by America or Europe alone.
لا يمكن حلهما بواسطة أمريكا أو أوروبا لوحدهما.
We cannot solve these problems unless we work together.
لا يمكننا حل هذه المشاكل إلا اذا عملنا سوياً.
So the great project of our generation, it seems to me,
لذا فالمشروع العظيم لجيلنا، كما يبدو لي،
is to build for the first time, out of a global ethic
هو بناء لأول مرة من نتاج الأخلاق العالمية
and our global ability to communicate
ومقدرتنا العالمية للإتصال
and organize together, a truly global society,
والتنظيم سوياً، مجتمع عالمي حقيقي،
built on that ethic but with institutions
مبني على تلك الأخلاق مع المؤسسات
that can serve that global society and make for a different future.
التي تستطيع خدمة المجتمع العالمي وصنع مستقبل مختلف.
We have now, and are the first generation with, the power to do this.
لدينا الآن، ولأول جيل مع، المقدرة لعمل ذلك.
Take climate change. Is it not absolutely scandalous
نأخذ تغير المناخ. أليس من المشين إطلاقاً
that we have a situation
أن لدينا أوضاع
where we know that there is a climate change problem,
حيث أننا نعلم أن هناك مشكلة تغير المناخ،
where we know also that that will mean we have to give more resources
حيث نعلم أيضاً أن ذلك سيعني بأننا يجب أن نقدم موارد أكثر
to the poorest countries to deal with that,
الى الدول الأكثر فقراً للتعامل مع ذلك،
when we want to create a global carbon market,
حينما نريد خلق سوق عالمي للكربون،
but there is no global institution
لكن ليس هناك مؤسسة عالمية
that people have been able to agree upon
قد تمكن الناس من الإتفاق عليها
to deal with this problem?
للتعامل مع هذه المشكلة؟
One of the things that has got to come out of Copenhagen in the next few months
أحد الأشياء التي يجب أن تخرج من كوبنهاغن في الأشهر القليلة القادمة
is an agreement that there will be
هو الإتفاق على أنه سيكون هناك
a global environmental institution
مؤسسة عالمية للبيئة
that is able to deal
بمقدورها التعامل
with the problems of persuading the whole of the world
مع المشاكل التي تقنع كل العالم
to move along a climate-change agenda.
للتحرك بجانب جدول أعمال تغير المناخ
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
One of the reasons why an institution is not in itself enough
أحد الأسباب لماذا المؤسسة نفسها ليست كافية
is that we have got to persuade people around the world
هو أننا يجب أن نقنع الناس حول العالم
to change their behavior as well,
لتغيير تصرفاتهم أيضاً،
so you need that global ethic of fairness and responsibility
لذا نحتاج لأخلاق عالمية للعدل والمسئولية
across the generations.
عبر الأجيال.
Take the financial crisis.
نأخذ الأزمة المالية.
If people in poorer countries can be hit by a crisis that starts in New York
اذا كان الناس في الدول الأكثر فقراً يعانون من أزمة بدأت في نيويورك
or starts in the sub-prime market of the United States of America.
أو بدأت في سوق الرهن العقاري الثانوي في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية.
If people can find that that sub-prime product
اذا كان بمقدور الناس الحصول على ذلك المنتج الثانوي
has been transferred across nations
الذي ينتقل عبر الأمم
many, many times until it ends up in banks in Iceland
الكثير، الكثير من الوقت حتى ينتهي في بنوك في آيسلاندا
or the rest in Britain,
أو بقية أنحاء بريطانيا،
and people's ordinary savings are affected by it,
ومدخرات الناس العاديون تتأثر بها،
then you cannot rely on a system of national supervision.
حينها لا تستطيع الإعتماد على نظام للمراقبة الوطنية.
You need in the long run for stability, for economic growth,
تحتاج على المدى الطويل للإستقرار، للنمو الإقتصادي،
for jobs, as well as for financial stability,
للوظائف، مثلها مثل الإستقرار المالي،
global economic institutions that make sure
مؤسسات الإقتصاد الدولية التي تتأكد
that growth to be sustained has to be shared,
بأن النمو المستدام يجب تقاسمه،
and are built on the principle
ومبني على أُسس
that the prosperity of this world is indivisible.
أن إزدهار هذا العالم غير قابل للتجزئة.
So another challenge for our generation is to create global institutions
اذاً تحدي آخر لجيلنا هو خلق المؤسسات العالمية
that reflect our ideas of fairness and responsibility,
التي تعكس أفكارنا للعدالة والمسئولية،
not the ideas that were the basis
ليست الأفكار التي كانت أسس
of the last stage of financial development over these recent years.
المراحل الأخيرة للنمو المالي خلال السنوات القليلة الماضية.
Then take development and take the partnership we need between our countries
بعدها خذ التنمية وخذ الشراكة التي نحتاجها بين بلداننا
and the rest of the world, the poorest part of the world.
وبقية العالم، الجزء الأفقر للعالم.
We do not have the basis of a proper partnership for the future,
ليس لدينا أسس الشراكة الصحيحة للمستقبل،
and yet, out of people’s desire for a global ethic
وحتى الآن، من رغبة الناس لأخلاق عالمية
and a global society that can be done.
ومجتمع عالمي يمكن صنعه.
I have just been talking to the President of Sierra Leone.
كنت أتحدث مع رئيس سيرلاليون قبل قليل.
This is a country of six and a half million people,
هذه الدولة التي يبلغ تعداد سكانها ستة ملايين ونصف،
but it has only 80 doctors; it has 200 nurses;
لكن لديها فقط 80 طبيباً، ولديها 200 ممرض،
it has 120 midwives.
لديها 120 قابلة.
You cannot begin to build a healthcare system for six million people
لا يمكنك الشروع في بناء نظام صحي لستة ملايين نسمة
with such limited resources.
مع هذه الموارد المحدودة.
Or take the girl I met when I was in Tanzania,
نأخذ الفتاة التي إلتقيتها عندما كنت في تنزانيا،
a girl called Miriam.
فتاة تسمى مريم.
She was 11 years old; her parents had both died from AIDS,
كان عمرها 11 سنة، توفي والديها بسبب مرض الإيدز،
her mother and then her father.
أمها وبعد ذلك أبوها.
She was an AIDS orphan being handed
كانت يتيمة بفعل الإيدز سُلمت
across different extended families to be cared for.
مع مختلف الأسر الممتدة للعناية بهم.
She herself was suffering from HIV;
هي نفسها كانت تعاني من الإيدز،
she was suffering from tuberculosis.
كانت تعاني من السُل.
I met her in a field, she was ragged, she had no shoes.
إلتقيتها في حقل، كانت خشنة، لم يكن لديها حذاء.
When you looked in her eyes, any girl at the age of eleven
عندما تنظر الى عينيها، كل فتاة في عمر الحادية عشر
is looking forward to the future,
تتطلع الى المستقبل،
but there was an unreachable sadness in that girl’s eyes
لكن كان هناك حزن لا نهائي في عيون تلك الفتاة
and if I could have translated that to the rest of the world for that moment,
واذا أستطعت ترجمة ذلك الى بقية أنحاء العالم لتلك اللحظة،
I believe that all the work that it had done for the global HIV/AIDS fund
أعتقد أن ذلك كل العمل الذي قامت به على الصعيد العالمي لدعم الإيدز
would be rewarded by people being prepared to make donations.
سيكون مكافأة للناس الجاهزين لتقديم التبرعات.
We must then build a proper relationship between the richest and
يجب علينا اذاً بناء علاقة صحيحة بين الدول الغنية
the poorest countries
والدول الأكثر فقراً
based on our desire that they are able to fend for themselves
تستند على رغبتنا في أن يصبحوا قادرين على إعالة أنفسهم
with the investment that is necessary in their agriculture,
بالإستثمار الضروري لزراعتهم،
so that Africa is not a net importer of food, but an exporter of food.
حتى أن افريقيا ليست مستورداً صافياً للغذاء، لكن مصدراً للغذاء.
Take the problems of human rights and
نأخذ مشكلة حقوق الإنسان و
the problems of security in so many countries around the world.
مشاكل الأمن في عديد من البلدان حول العالم.
Burma is in chains, Zimbabwe is a human tragedy,
بورما في الأغلال، زيمبابوي هي مأساة إنسانية،
in Sudan thousands of people have died unnecessarily
وفي السودان مات الآلاف من الناس بغير ضرورة
for wars that we could prevent.
لحروب كان بمقدورنا منعها.
In the Rwanda Children's Museum,
في متحف رواندا للأطفال،
there is a photograph of a 10-year-old boy
هناك صورة لطفل عمره 10 سنوات
and the Children's Museum is commemorating the lives that were lost
ومتحف الطفل يحي ذكرى الأرواح التي زُهقت
in the Rwandan genocide where a million people died.
في الإبادة الجماعية في رواندا حيث مات ملايين الناس.
There is a photograph of a boy called David.
كانت هناك صورة لصبي أسمه ديفيد.
Beside that photograph there is the information about his life.
بجانب الصورة هناك معلومات عن حياته.
It said "David, age 10."
وهي تقول "ديفيد، عمره 10."
David: ambition to be a doctor.
ديفيد: طموحه أن يصبح طبيباً.
Favorite sport: football. What did he enjoy most?
رياضته المفضلة: كرة القدم. ما يمتعه أكثر؟
Making people laugh.
جعل الناس يضحكون.
How did he die?
كيف مات؟
Tortured to death.
تم تعذيبه حتى الموت.
Last words said to his mother who was also tortured to death:
آخر كلمة قالها لأمه التي هي أيضاً عُذبت حتى الموت:
"Don't worry. The United Nations are coming."
"لا تقلقي. الأمم المتحدة قادمة."
And we never did.
ولم نفعلها نحن.
And that young boy believed our promises
وصدّق ذلك الولد الصغير وعودنا
that we would help people in difficulty in Rwanda,
أننا سنساعد الناس في مصاعبهم في رواندا،
and we never did.
ولم نفعل ذلك نحن.
So we have got to create in this world also
لذا يتعين علينا صنع في هذا العالم أيضاً
institutions for peacekeeping and humanitarian aid,
مؤسسات حفظ السلام والمساعدات الإنسانية،
but also for reconstruction and security
وأيضاً لإعادة الإعمار والأمن
for some of the conflict-ridden states of the world.
لبعض الدول التي تعاني من الصراعات في العالم.
So my argument today is basically this.
اذا كلامي اليوم هو في الأساس.
We have the means by which we could create a truly global society.
لدينا الوسائل التي عبرها نقدر على صنع مجتمع عالمي حقيقي.
The institutions of this global society can be created by our endeavors.
مؤسسات هذا المجتمع العالمي يمكن صنعها بواسطة مساعينا.
That global ethic can infuse the fairness and responsibility that is necessary
تلك الأخلاق العالمية التي يمكنها بث العدالة والمسئولية الضرورية
for these institutions to work,
لعمل هذه المؤسسات،
but we should not lose the chance in this generation,
لكن لا يجب علينا تفويت الفرصة في هذا الجيل،
in this decade in particular, with President Obama in America,
في هذا العقد تحديداً، مع الرئيس أوباما في أمريكا،
with other people working with us around the world,
مع بقية الناس يعملون معنا حول العالم،
to create global institutions for the environment,
لخلق مؤسسات عالمية من أجل البيئة،
and for finance,
ومن أجل المالية،
and for security and for development,
ومن أجل الأمن ومن أجل التنمية،
that make sense of our responsibility to other peoples,
التي تعطي معنى لمسئوليتنا تجاه بقية الناس،
our desire to bind the world together, and
رغبتنا في ربط العالم سوياً، و
our need to tackle problems that everybody knows exist.
و حاجتنا للتعامل مع المشاكل التي يعرف الجميع وجودها.
It is said that in Ancient Rome that when Cicero spoke to his audiences,
يقال أنه في روما القديمة عندما كان سيسرو يتحدث الى الحضور،
people used to turn to each other and say about Cicero, "Great speech."
إعتاد الناس أن يتبادلوا مع بعضهم البعض ويقولوا عن سيسرو ، "حديث عظيم."
But it is said that in Ancient Greece
لكن قيل أنه في اليونان القديمة
when Demosthenes spoke to his audiences,
عندما تحدث ديموسينس الى الحضور،
people turned to each other and didn’t say "Great speech."
يلتفت الناس الى بعضهم البعض ولا يقولوا "حديث عظيم."
They said, "Let's march."
يقولوا، "هيا نسير ."
We should be marching towards a global society.
يجب علينا السير تجاه مجتمعنا العالمي.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)